Guide to the William Shenstone Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Shenstone papers
1726-1979
1751-1770
OSB MSS 63
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
The papers concern the Leasowes estate, including correspondence with Shenstone's attorney Thomas Milward and others about his legal and financial difficulties; mortgages and indentures on the property; documents concerning the case of Dolman vs. Shenstone and the settlement of his estate after his death; and surveys, descriptions and engravings of the Leasowes. The collection also contains engraved portraits of Shenstone; verses addressed to him by friends, including Robert Dodsley and Lady Luxborough; and an autograph copy of his "The Snuff-box."
Shenstone, William, 1714-1763
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WILLIAM SHENSTONE, 1714-1763
William Shenstone was born in Halesowen, Worcestershire on November 13, 1714. He was educated first in a dame school run by Sarah Lloyd, whom he celebrated in his poem "The Schoolmistress," then at the Halesowen grammar school. In 1732 he matriculated at Pembroke College, Oxford, where his friends included the writers Richard Jago and Richard Graves.
A small volume of his poetry was privately printed at Oxford in 1737, and "The Judgement of Hercules" and "The Schoolmistress" appeared anonymously in 1741 and 1742. Shenstone was enrolled at Oxford until 1742, but took no degree.
After the death of his guardian Thomas Dolman in 1745, Shenstone moved onto the Leasowes estate and devoted his life and more than his income to improving the grounds and gardens. The ferme ornée style of ornamented landscaping at The Leasowes was an important influence on later English landscape gardening (a term Shenstone may have originated), and the grounds became "a place to be visited by travellers, and copied by designers," as Johnson noted.
Shenstone's occasional poetry continued to appear in Robert Dodsley's Collection of Poems (1748, 1755, 1758), and his friends and correspondents included several literary figures, among them William Somerville, Joseph Spence, Joseph Grainger, Thomas Percy, and the actor Thomas Hull, as well as Lady Luxborough.
In early 1763, Shenstone hoped to be granted a pension by Lord Bute, and visited Lord Stamford in pursuit of it. Unfortunately, during his return home he developed a chill and a "putrid fever," and died on February 11, 1763. The unmarried Shenstone had no direct heirs, and left his financially embarrassed estate to his cousin, John Hodgetts. Dodsley published his three-volume Works, which included Shenstone's essay "Unconnected Thoughts on Gardening," in 1764-69.
Scope and Contents
The William Shenstone Papers consist of correspondence, legal and financial documents, and printed material related to the poet William Shenstone and his estate, The Leasowes. The papers span the dates 1726-1979, but the bulk of the material dates from the 1750s and 1760s. The papers are housed in one box and have been organized into four series.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged in two subseries. The first, William Shenstone Correspondence, contains letters by and to Shenstone, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Folders 5-10 hold Shenstone's letters to his estate manager and attorney Thomas Milward, most concerning the lands inherited by Shenstone from his guardian Thomas Dolman but contested by Dolman's other heirs. The second subseries, Thomas Milward (Estate) Correspondence, contains third-party letters to Milward on various business matters, chronologically arranged.
Series II, Financial Papers, consists of miscellaneous bills and receipts pertaining to Shenstone and is housed in folders 18-22.
Series III, Legal Papers, is arranged in two subseries. Dolman v. Shenstone, found in folders 23-33, contains the progress of the writs pertaining to the dispute over the Halesowen inheritance, from the original deed signed by William Penn of Harborough Hall (grandfather of both parties), through the final agreement to partition the estate. Other Legal (Estate) Papers are located in folders 34-43 and include farm mortgages, indentures, and the complete text of a Chancery Brief filed against Shenstone's heirs by his former housekeeper Mary Cutler, alleging nonpayment of wages, interest and 500 pounds to "settle her in the world without going into any other or new service in case of his Death as he had very frequently said it was his intention and design she never should."
Series IV, Other Papers, is housed in folders 44-58. The first subseries, William Shenstone, contains mostly printed material, including engraved portraits of Shenstone and pages from a printing of "The Schoolmistress." The Leasowes includes 18th century engravings of views of the gardens, mounted newspaper clippings concerning the estate, a portion of a poem, "The Leasowes," a map and description from an 1865 freehold auction announcement, and a copy of a 1979 article by John Riely on the development of the gardens.
Female domestics -- Great Britain; Gardens -- England -- Design; Gardens, English -- Design; Poets, English -- Homes and haunts -- England; Wages -- Household employees; Leasowes Garden (Halesowen, England); Dodsley, Robert, 1704-1764; Luxborough, Henrietta Knight, Baroness, 1699-1756; Shenstone, William, 1714-1763
- Correspondence, Series I
  - WILLIAM SHENSTONE CORRESPONDENCE
    - Hodgetts, John. ALS to Mr. Clarke; Snowhill, Burmingham, 1766 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      John Hodgetts was executor of Shenstone's will.
    - Milward, Thomas. ALS to William Shenstone, 1762 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Reynolds, Robert (clerk to a Mr. Crawley). ALS to William Shenstone, 1755 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Shenstone, William. ALS (copy) to Thomas Holbeache, 1760 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Shenstone, William. 2 ALS to Elizabeth Milward, 1759, 1760 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Shenstone, William. 27 ALS to Mr. Thomas Milward, 1755-61 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - THOMAS MILWARD (ESTATE) CORRESPONDENCE
    - ALS from Thomas Dolman; Broom, 1753 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 3 ALS from Elizabeth Milward, 1755-56 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS from John Ingram, 1756 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS from H. Roberts Jr., 1758 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 4 ALS from Thomas Holbeache, 1759-60 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - ALS from Rowland Hill; Be[waley?], 1761 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS from J. Pixell, 1767 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Financial Papers, 1753-56; Series II
  - Accounting of Shenstone's Receipts and Disbursements, 1753-56 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Mr.Shenstone's Further bill from Milward", 1758 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Holbeache's bill to Mr. Dolman and Shenstone", 1761 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Mr.Shenstone's Further bill from Milward", 1761 Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bill, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Legal Papers, Series III
  - DOLMAN V. SHENSTONE
    - Deed concerning Esther Penn, 1726 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Signed by William Penn, William Penn Jr., and Ann Shenstone
    - Bill of complaint by Dolman, 1726 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      With observations in Shenstone's hand
    - Notice of intent to execute complaint, 1755 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Rough draft of Shenstone's answer in Chancery., [1755-56?] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notes by Shenstone on a draft, [1755-56?] (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Draft answer for Shenstone in Chancery with notes by Shenstone, 1755-56 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Proposal for division of lands, 1756 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Signed by H. Hollier
    - Proposal for division of the estate, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Proposals for divisions, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Amended bill of complaint by Thomas Dolman, 1756 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Draft answer to amended bill of complaint, 1756 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Note on date of partition of estate, 1760 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - OTHER LEGAL (ESTATE) PAPERS
    - "An abstract of William Shenstone's title to the Ivey Estate in Halesowen Parish in the county of Salop", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Indenture between William Shenstone and Paul White, 1758 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Deed between Willian Shenstone and Paul White concerning earlier indenture, 1758 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - AN to Thomas Milward from Paul White; Kinver, 1759 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Indenture between William Shenstone and Edward Davies, 1756 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Mortgage Deed between William Shenstone and William Davies, 1760 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Draft surrender of the mortgage by Davies (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Indenture between Paul White, Edward Toye, and William Shenstone, 1761 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Indenture between William Shenstone, Samuel Spencer, and John Spencer, 1758 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Chancery Brief: Cutler agt. Davies, 1764-65 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Mary Cutler representing the creditors of the Shenstone Estate; William Davies representing the Shenstone Estate
- Other Papers, Series IV
  - WILLIAM SHENSTONE
    - Untitled verses in Greek, Latin and English in unidentified hand (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "The Snuff Box": facsimile of Shenstone autograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "The School-Mistress": printed, mounted and incomplete (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Three portrait engravings of Shenstone, 1795, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Two versions of the 1795 engraving after W. G. Waldron, one in color
    - Four engraved pages from the 1791 Works, in Verse and Prose, mounted (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - "Family of Shenstone the Poet," by H. Sydney Grazebook: printed, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - THE LEASOWES
    - "Leasowes farm as surveyed by Mr. William Lowe", 1759 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Original and printed version
    - "Whitacre's farm at Churchill as surveyed by Mr. Lowe", 1760 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - "The LEASOWES, A Poem", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Printed. Incomplete
    - "A Description of the Leasowes, the Seat of the Late Willam Shenstone, Esq" by Robert Dodsley (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Printed, mounted on album stock, and incomplete. Includes verses addressed to Shenstone by Dodsley and others
    - Newspaper clippings and articles concerning the Leasowes, 1772-99 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Mounted on album stock
    - Engravings of views at Leasowes and Halesowen, 1775-1822, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
      "A View in Virgil's Grove" is hand-colored; most mounted on album stock
    - "The Leasowes as in the time of Shenstone A.D 17__, drawn by Arthur Dixon from a sketch by Mr. Dovaston", 1838 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - "The Leasows Estate" (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Map and description from a freehold auction announcement ("Lot 10"), 1865
    - Riely, John. "Shenstone's Walks: the Genesis of The Leasowes", 1979 Sep (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Printed. Article originally published in Apollo.